[Music]
hello you found the portal I'm your host
Eric Weinstein and we're here this
evening a little bit later than usual
with my friend and presidential
candidate Andrew yang Andrew welcome
thank you for keeping the portal open
late for an oh my rad thanks for
bringing the energy you just come fresh
off this rally MacArthur Park your
indefatigable the Energizer Bunny yes we
just had a 6,000 person rally 7,000
8,000 I lost track I was counting Manuel
Aquino wasn't but and I should say that
your hat is make America think harder
yep but if the portals all about it
smacked it while we're trying we're
trying so we don't want to keep you up
late because we want you supercharged
for tomorrow so let's just dig right
into it
Andrew I'm remembering that we were
having this dinner at za Z in San
Francisco and you were impressing the
hell out of my wife and myself and I
said that guys going places she says how
can t is it it's these are different
times oh thank you so am i right but
this is a this is happening oh it's
happening big time I mean our campaign
is growing by leaps and bounds by all of
the measurements you would ordinarily
measure a presidential campaign crowd
size fundraising novice ISM components
yeah I guess the yang gang is absolutely
fanatical trust me I encountered them
all the time on social media well I love
the yang gang Thank You yang gang
yeah the excitement is palpable and I
love it I mean everywhere I go now
people will just say like I support you
and give me a fist bump and and
certainly when we campaign I mean now we
draw crowds of other hundreds or
thousands depending upon where we are
it's amazing now let's just dig into it
we're in this totally bizarre situation
I don't think the institutions have
faced up to just how dire our situation
is when I go outside for the most part
the physical world is still humming
along but everywhere else you can see
the signs that some have the
superstructure that undergirds
the simple physical reality thing am I
wrong about that no I I agree with you
you know and and in in many ways if
you're just living life not plugged into
all of the institutional decay then you
just go out in the sun shining and the
birds are chirping and you know like you
said the physical world is still more or
less sound barring the occasional heat
wave and an unseasonal weather pattern
so the way I see it effectively what you
have is a world of institutions and you
have the wrong people in the
institutions in fact what's happened is
somehow that the institutions were built
in an era where things were growing
rapidly the growth pattern changed a
heck of a long time ago almost 50 years
ago and so for what they've done is they
these institutions have selected for
people who can continue to tell stories
about growth and to kind of play games
to keep the illusion that everything is
still humming along as if it was the 50s
and 60s but that hasn't been true for a
long time how far off am i well that's
what the numbers saying and I'm a
numbers guy where if you look at the
economy of the 70s you had a certain
level of buying power among the middle
class and certain split in terms of the
gains from the economy among different
parts of society and then the lines
start to diverge starting in the 70s and
now they're incredibly divergent where
you have middle-class incomes
essentially unchanged during that time
and then people at the very top level
absorbing more more and more of the
gains in the winner-take-all economy but
we all pretend like it's still the 70s
and you can see the disconnect in the
the lived experience of most Americans
in mostly country where they're trying
to catch on that things have changed and
it's dark it's it's dark it's what's
incredibly dark and it's it's worth
laughing about I think for that reason
because if we don't have a sense of
humor about it we're not going to be
able to easily do the work so I think
whistling past the graveyard and and
gallows humor definitely there's there's
a place for that well I you know I
naturally I suppose people have said to
me that I have a very dystopian
point of view but I tend to present it
in a positive upbeat manner I think
you're trying to get us through a
bottleneck that you and I both know is
coming and that in essence I mean one of
the things I'm very concerned about with
you is that I don't want you to promise
the world that you know how to do this I
want you just to say that I'm the best
person data but whatever is coming next
because nobody knows what to do well
certainly I would never claim I'm nishan
sore that I'm gonna get everything right
I mean I make mistakes all the time to
ask my wife she'd be like yeah you
screwed up the other day but we you and
I were talking before the camera started
rolling that I think it's going to be a
very dark time and the goal has to be to
try and survive the darkness and not
have it produce existential level harm
and I believe that I can assist in that
regard but I certainly would never say
that like I have all the answers or that
if I'm president everything's gonna work
right because the fact is there there
are two things I've thought about it's
like there's the way the president makes
you feel right and then there is
actually solving problems on the ground
and right now our experience of the
presidency tends to be around a feeling
like if Donald Trump does something
irrational it really does not affect my
day-to-day existence except for the fact
that I see all the news reports and oh
my god that guy what's he doing you know
and the same is true in Reverse like if
Barack Obama did something decent and
human it made me feel good didn't
necessarily you know like change my
commute sure
and so there's there's the way it makes
us feel which I believe I can assist
with just about immediately for anyone
who you know wants someone who seems
solutions-oriented right positive and
positive they did data friendly yeah
they're friendly and genuinely wants to
just try and make people's lives better
I think that would make people feel
better but then there's the reality of
trying to solve the problems from the
perch at the top of the government yeah
and that's a very different process
you know I'm locked in on this idea of a
freedom dividend in part
because I think it's the most
dramatically positive thing we could do
that we could actually effectuate in
real life that would improve people's
lives that we can actually get done now
I am both positive and negative about it
as you probably remember what my belief
is is that we have two claims as
Americans we have a claim as a
contributor to the economy and we have a
claim as a sole because we happen to
live here and as a soul we have certain
rights as a human being just as a member
of society the weaker of the two is as a
soul but that claim still exists and in
some sense what you're calling the
freedom dividend or universal basic
income speaks to the idea that there are
these two competing claims and you you
don't want to get rid of the incentive
structure that allows people to you know
take a dream and turn it into something
I love the dream I love work I love
entrepreneurship yeah and this is people
doing great stuff so I think that
there's a theory that there's sort of a
series of economic theories that haven't
actually been developed and I think one
of the things that's really important to
me is that we retake the institutions
because what we've done is we've
selected for people who have used very
simplistic models that have had a huge
effect on transferring wealth but have
not actually mirrored our our problems
we've selected for the people who really
don't tell the truth and I'm very
worried how let's talk about your your
your first term in office which is gonna
happen 21 who are you inauguration day
it's gonna be a blast you're gonna be
there P is gonna be there yang Yang is
gonna be there and have a giant party
wait wait wait wait a second get ahead
of us who are you gonna staff your
government with if you're gonna have the
same problem that everybody has which
once you've caught once the dog catches
the car then what you've got all of
these institutions which have selected
four economists who don't tell the truth
who who've selected four sociologists
who are friendly to the institutions and
hostile to our people what do we do my
team is going to be a blend of different
people with different experience
that's from different industries even
different ideologies and I think you
need some people who are DC insiders who
have relationships on Capitol Hill if
you really want to get things done
because you're talking about possibly
the most institutionalized town in our
society and so if you get there and just
like I'm gonna staff it with outsiders
then nobody does Trump's problem yeah
like you're not gonna get anything done
you're you're just going to be fighting
with the system all the time that
they're gonna be like these antibodies
that treat you like this hostile agent
and then they're going to just make your
life miserable at every turn I mean that
that's just the way organizations work
its way cultures work and so you need to
have a blend of people that are like
look hey I get it
I'm a new figure and you're concerned
and one of my principles is that I don't
fault people for the incentives that
have formed them mmm-hmm and but by this
what I mean is like if you show up in DC
and there's someone who's been part of
the fabric of DC for twenty plus years
and they are someone who been through
administrations right and left is sort
of survived the whole thing and their
goal is to just keep that function going
and make sure they get to retirement and
whatnot like you can't blame that person
for being part of that system because
that's what their events items have been
for years and years and so what you
don't want to do is you don't want to
get there and be like I'm gonna like
turn everything upside down I'm like
attack everyone with the immune system
we'll just actually you know the
macrophages will descend on you and yeah
and then you'll never get anything done
ever anything that so that was one of
the answers that I was dying to hear
which is I'm gonna have to work with the
infrastructure that's already there but
then there's the second part of it which
is that I actually need to see some
people permanently ejected called out
chastise who have been this class of
people miss advising our government
throughout the 80s 90s early part of the
century well and that's a dark part for
all of us that we sense that there's
really limited accountability in DC like
you can give bad advice and screw
something up and you keep your job
Tagg still there like it like no one
goes back and says hey your white paper
turns out it was completely mistaken
like that hey that's not the way that
town works or that you know many
government institutions work so that's
the challenge is that you have to try
and make changes within this incredibly
institutionalized environment and so you
need a combination of people that are
well intended you bring them in and say
look there's gonna feel like brain
damage you're gonna come in right and
you're gonna be like especially if you
can't come in with the background like
you and I might have from technology or
entrepreneurship where you look up and
you'd be like wait you have how many
people doing what and you're not allowed
to do what you know it's like the the
story of like healthcare.gov where like
the website didn't work in part because
they hired a giant consulting firm and
they had all these bureaucratic
processes and then when the website
didn't work you know what they did they
hired a bunch of maverick Valley types
and through the red date by the window
or that did a repair job so the the goal
has to be to bring in Patriots who
understand that they're not going to
have like an enjoyable time trying to
turn the battleship but that if they
turn the battleship three degrees to the
right they can do more good similar they
were in another environment where they
turned it you know like Andrew I think
we're in a much more revolutionary
situation and in part to energize people
I mean what we're talking about is a
Revenge of competency a revenge of
genius a revenge of people who actually
know how to do things and care enough
who are ready and want to be mobilized
and want to be called up who have been
sitting you know with major-league
skills and did the minors or worse and
the fact is is that what the
institutions have done have inverted the
competency hierarchy I mean you know
there's a guy that I don't understand
named Brad DeLong who was part of the
group that brought in NAFTA and they
they helped to sell this idea that free
trade was good for everybody and then
years later I hear oh you know what free
trade actually
there was an esoteric version an
exoteric version the exoteric version we
put on display for everybody we always
knew that the in the esoteric version
that was shared in the seminar rooms
that it was a social Darwinist welfare
function that rewarded you by the cube
of your wealth and I just sit there with
my jaw on the floor thinking what did
you just say and then he says like I
don't understand maybe we hurt people in
Ohio but we helped a lot of Mexican
peasants and I'm thinking so you think
that the American voters who you've
called jingoistic and you know alt
ultra-nationalists are going to be very
happy that you've denigrated their
patriotism and now what they have to
show for it is is that there are Mexican
peasants who are significantly better at
which I mean who doesn't want Mexican
peasants to be better off but for sake I
mean this is this is a class of people
that needs to lose yeah and a lot of
them are gonna lose or my administration
like I'm not a generally vindictive
person no it's that I look you know so I
hope he has a happy wonderful life yeah
exactly it's a kind of thing where it's
like hey guess what you had a lot of
influence and authority in one ERA it's
over now like you know not going to
unduly but trying to make your life
miserable or anything but you know
exactly where there's nothing vindictive
it's just I don't want to watch the Alan
Greenspan show or the Larry Summers show
or the Paul Krugman I don't really need
there's no reason that these people get
to be in every scene in every decade ad
infinitum yeah again like I said there's
really no accountability for being wrong
and so if someone presided over an era
where you know there was epic
mismanagement um you know we still are
asking them what the heck they think can
I hit you with another one that's really
comical for me sure I watch the graphics
that have your name in in relationship
to the other competitors and I know who
the network's are afraid of and they're
afraid of you they'll do a linear
perspective graphic and you'll be the
guy on the very far end and the
presenter will stand to notice that that
does seem to be something about well I
don't think you should be bringing it up
I think the job is for people like me to
be bringing
this up because they've been playing
this game with like Ron Paul with Bernie
Sanders and I don't know if you're
familiar in magic with the concept of
magician's choice no I'm not so a
magician
it engages in a trick with magicians
choice let's say that I want you to
choose C out of a B and C so I give you
the option pick two you pick a and B and
I say okay I'll take those away so now
we'll look at C or if you pick a and C
I'll say okay we'll take one of those
two will throw B away now which one do
you so eventually you think you've made
a decision but in fact the whole game
was is that the magician was pushing you
without your knowledge and it's like
what idea companies choice this is what
I think it's a media companies choice
and we've got a situation where my
feeling is that the more the yang gang
can find and this goes for tulsi gabbard
or whoever else might be sidelined by
this game my feeling is is that what
you're on right now is the equivalent of
pirate radio this is some is dot for the
American people and we sure you know
it's one reason I'm here man when it's
one of the reasons that we need to make
sure that these channels are opened to
the very people that the DNC doesn't
want running or the network's don't want
running and the thing that I hate is is
that we're in this William Tell
situation where we've got to run against
our own party yeah well you know again
and you may not want to say that and I
understand why but I'll be damned if I'm
gonna listen to a situation in which you
were you're shut out of air time and
you're pushed off to the side of the
graphic thank you Eric and I can say
that this man is the head of pirate
radio for the 21st century
certainly one of the high chiefs of it
and to me again you know you have these
institutions with certain incentives and
certain relationships and they're going
to be naturally protective of the folks
that they think are on the inside and be
naturally very leery of the people that
they think are on the outside but one of
the themes of this era is that there are
more of us on the outside that are
catching
and that the stranglehold that media
companies had on our attention has
weakened significantly it's one reason
why someone like me can do so well in
this environment or that someone like
you can become this independent
intellectual voice that doesn't need to
you know like get a CNN contributor
contract or whatever that was very funny
one of the members of The Washington
Post which you know says that democracy
dies in darkness not their tagline but
one of them said that everything you
Eric you have to say that's new isn't
true and everything you say that's true
isn't new so it's like remarkably
there's nothing I can possibly
contribute to the conversation it's been
said Eric yeah Ben the only stuff that
hasn't is wrong so what I'd love to do
is to talk about some some sort of new
ideas to undergird some of the economic
things that you and I have traditionally
talked about more before your meteoric
rise so let's dig into it now please
okay so one of the things that pieces I
want to say that I quote this man all
the time I've learned a great deal from
him and his wife and that he's one of
the most profound economic thinkers that
I've encountered and I met a lot of
fucking people you're very kind sir and
one of the things that I would say is
that even when I disagree with you even
on your signature stuff that the way I
really view you is is that you're the
candidate who is most open to new ideas
and you're always up for a good
discussion a good argument and you'll go
with whatever's best and I find that you
are as close to non egoic as anyone I've
met Renny I mean you really seem to be
running out of compulsion yeah you know
I don't have any native desire to be
President I didn't feel that you ever
did was one of the reasons I love the
fact that you're running yeah I I think
about one of my main qualifications to
be President yeah is that I just don't
socialize that much in the sense of like
if you have me around a bunch of fancy
stuff like it really doesn't do anything
for me like you know as president I
would love to do away with a lot of the
you do like Kiki
the ceremony like it seems like like
it's counterproductive and no III have I
haven't I think that might help me do a
better job so let's try to geek out on a
couple of ideas that P and I have been
playing with see what you think yeah I
love it okay so one of the things that
we've been thinking about is some people
start talking about the difference
between the shareholder economy of the
past and the stakeholder economy of the
future yeah there are other issues about
the dignity of work and what happens
when machines replace you you can't
necessarily defend yourself economically
but you still have a reason to get up in
the morning and do something oh we hope
you have a reason there you get up and
do something amen
now the thing is we've been thinking
about this paradigm from object-oriented
programming which is the difference
between is ax versus has ax so if a
Lamborghini can play a an FM broadcast
through its speaker you could
technically find out that by some
definition the labrum borghini is a
radio but that seems absurd it's much
it's more sane to say that it has a
radio just the way it has a transmission
we make this error I think when we talk
about workers we say that person is a
worker they are a bricklayer or or a
teamster you know completely and that
what we need to do is to readjust our
model of an economic agent to a has a
model and so the idea is that you may
have a breadwinner and you also have a
contributor and you also have a consumer
and therefore what it is that we do all
day long in the face of the of the
automation that may or may not get here
in dribs and drabs or come as a wave we
don't know that we need to have a model
of humans that recognizes a need to be
active in the economy whether or not the
marginal product of our labor is
sufficient to take care of our family
yeah I I love it so much and I couldn't
agree more
ok so that that would be the kind of a
research program that we would love to
try to see under girding a new week
economy that recognizes a much richer
concept of an agent but without it I'm
worried that you know the sort of the
power of that chicago-style thinking
pushes us back into humans as widgets
well humans as widgets is predominant
and you can see it at every turn or even
if you ask a kid what do you want to be
when you grow up it's you know they'll
say I want to be a fireman astronaut
baker scientist whatever it happens to
be and by the numbers we are more work
obsessed now than we perhaps have ever
been and trying to break up our
identities sure into several aspects
where you take a trucker who's on the
road away from his family four days a
week and say you know you're a dad
you're like a consumer of of hunting
gear or you know like you there's more
to you than being a trucker when they
have shaped their life around being a
trucker because you know it's literally
you're behind the wheel for 14 hours a
day you get out you sleep at a rest stop
I mean these are all consuming types of
existences that are filled by hundreds
of thousands of American men and you
know ninety-four percent of them are men
so you know it's not like oh just things
are all men it's like come on 94% and so
if you were to go to that person and try
and have them adopt a more holistic
identity when they have essentially
shaped their entire existence around
their role in this real life like almost
circulatory system where it's like
they're piloting this blood vessel that
has a bunch of Home Depot crap in the
batter or whatever the heck they're
transporting like a daily basis having
them have other aspects of their
identity that they value to a point
where you could remove the work
component and they would you know be
cool with going home and
spending time with their their families
is pretty much the opposite of the way
our civilization functions right now
what we saw these deaths of despair
discussed by economists and in you know
the heartland of America we saw this
demographic crisis that happened when
this Soviet Union fell apart with you
know the mortality crisis all sorts of
people were dying of alcoholism heart
attacks and stress so this is a really
serious thing we had figure about the
restoration of human meaning and dignity
as different from employment you had
something like a dozen disenfranchised
taxi cab drivers and limo drivers kill
themselves you know last year like one
of whom two killed himself in front of
City Hall I mean like did his self
destruction cause meaningful ripples in
our society no most people watching this
listening is right now it's like oh that
should happen like you know that like
but this sort of self-destruction is
happening all the time and most of them
are just men quietly drinking themselves
to death in their homes Ryan you know
they're dead but well I love the idea
that you're talking about compassion for
men because one of the things that I'm
finding is that it's very tough to talk
in a know in a world that is currently
exploring this idea of toxic masculinity
from someplace that it might have been
reasonably defined and blowing it up
past past that point it's a very
dangerous thing to see a world that sort
of thinks that you know like all
straight white guys are okay when in
fact many of them are very vulnerable
and and by the numbers you by the
numbers right you know yeah it's so and
this is one of the themes that when you
talk about trying to define people by
different aspects of their life that
might have work as one of them but
rather like others the fact is I think
men struggle more with breaking up our
identities than women do because if you
were to say to a woman
hey you're a parent you're you know
sister your
right a nurse you're like all of these
things I think they would be more ready
to embrace some of the non work aspects
of their identity in part because of the
cultural load that is placed on
different types of yeah but I think I
think they're facing a big one coming up
which is that you're gonna have a huge
cohort of millennial females who pretty
much would would love to be in a
situation with meaningful work but also
with a family raising children of their
own and there's first of all it isn't
necessarily a supply of guys who can
rise to that I mean you know it doesn't
have to be traditional households but a
lot of it is gonna be male female
breadwinner somebody stays at home it
might be the woman who's in the
workforce might be the guy staying home
whatever the fact is a lot of these
families aren't going to form because
we're not in a position to say I can't
afford a 30-year mortgage I can see
enough stability in my future I can and
and that that's part of the thing is
that these challenges face us all in
different ways and it's really to me
counterproductive to disastrous to
single out a particular subset ups and
be like hey you've got it wrong you're
okay you know that's a legitimate you
know like thing to be upset about that
is not I mean like if if someone is
struggling like it ends up reaching
different groups in different ways right
and and you can't say it's like oh your
struggles are somehow more valid than
others so just to wrap around this
thought so I think that the division of
our identities into like work and
non-work right it's one of the greatest
things we have to overcome and by the
numbers if you lose your job and you're
a man you tend to have relatively
self-destructive patterns of behavior
manifest relatively consistently and
quickly we're unemployed men volunteer
less than employed men despite having
much more free time as
example substance abuse tends to go up
in very self-destructive behaviors a lot
of time spent on the computer goes up
which so that's a combination of gaming
and some other things and worn and porn
I'm sure is
you know I admit didn't I mean I kind of
implied it but was thinking you know
this is a free radio station effectively
and we're gonna be able to say that
that's one of the things that maybe
deranging us we don't know what its
effects are ya know so and that women
have struggles obviously but the
struggles take a different form in terms
of and the numbers show that women are
more adaptable to non work idleness
right that they will not show the same
patterns of self-destructive behavior
that men do now of course women
obviously you know hate to be unemployed
but the thing that I joke about that
sort of true is that women however are
never truly idle in the sense that they
always find like well this is a treat
like ways to be productive contributors
in a way that so many were struggle
examine where you're working for your
family taking care of elderly parents
your kids somebody else's kids these
things are part of the fabric of civil
society one of the questions I have is
should we talk about coming up with some
new financial products that get women
the money they need during the period of
their life
when they might need extra help in the
house when they when the the binds that
come from caring for elderly parents or
children are starting to knock them out
of the workforce and trying to figure
out how to make some kind of creative
structure to help shift the burdens to
times of their life when they can better
afford it what do you think about that
yeah so just to sort of show the other
side of the coin so men volunteered less
with their unemployed than employed even
though that doesn't make any sense in
terms of their free time women show
higher rates of volunteers have been
going back to school when they have more
more time so it's just that the numbers
show clear patterns of like different
responses to
you non-work-related
time or idleness but I'm with you in the
fact that right now trying to map
everyone's economic prospects to the the
market the markets valuation of our
wages right has all sorts of distorting
effects and what you're suggesting that
we should just start putting with money
into people's hands at various points in
their lives I mean that's really one of
the underpinnings of the freedom
dividend you know my part of it yeah
it's like you put a thousand bucks a
month into people's hands and then that
would allow us all to make different
types of decisions really from almost
day one of our adulthood yeah
all right let's try a few other things
that I think might be interesting one
thing that it wins presidential
campaigns we don't talk much about is
demographers demographers are sometimes
asked tell me some group of people that
we don't know about as a voting bloc
that nobody's figured out how to speak
to and I think I have a couple of these
that are candidates I liked oh please
yeah I'd like this maybe I'll find a new
audience too
Melvin okay so the first one that I have
you know so these are things like soccer
moms was one from years past or exurbs
between rural and suburbs where people
didn't realize that there were
intermediate places so here's one that I
think is huge that hasn't been
identified parents of super smart kids
that have some kind of a learning
difference that causes them to wildly
underperform in school this is something
that makes me crazy because I think it's
all over once you start seeing it you
see it everywhere
parents are tearing their hair out you
know teachers can't handle the kid nope
and there's just this maddening loss of
human brilliance that is flushed down
the toilet have you come up with a name
for this group
well I often refer to these as kids with
learning superpowers and I like I talked
about teaching disabilities which is the
more dangerous version of this that be
people don't fit into the notion of what
can be educated by one teacher teaching
a room of 30 people to make the
economics work my belief is that and
I'll come up with a name for it for you
but I want to talk to all of the parents
who are leading lives of despair saying
why is my kid wildly underperforming and
I know how smart this kid is why are we
doing this to ourselves and why will no
one speak to it
this is by the way this is me and it's
been in my family it's me four five
generation you really well yeah I'm very
public about the fact that my older son
is autistic you know that and that when
we put him in various environments I
mean there were very very sharp
struggles and to me atypical is the new
normal
like neurologically atypical and you're
right that as soon as you start seeing
it you see it everywhere and that the
facts show that it's incredibly
commonplace and at this point I think
most American families have someone
other in the family or someone in their
social circles that resembles the
description that you just put out there
of this group to me a lot of it is that
our institutions just aren't aren't well
designed for people with different
learning profiles or different and yet
these are just very often the people are
gonna found new fields we're gonna find
new drugs for us who are gonna think in
such different a uncorrelated fashions
that these are very often the people
that I value the most and you never know
whether things gonna work out because
the kid every every year is sustaining
more and more trauma
yeah whereas these other kids it's like
you know I remember looking at the
neurotypical z-- as if you know if I was
like Cinderella watching all the other
sisters go to the ball and I was sitting
there scrubbing dishes like what you
know every conference was Erika's
underperforming Eric can't meet his
potential Eric was that you know it's at
some point it's just like you don't
realize how much damage you're doing to
maybe as much as a fifth of the country
well someone described it as like you're
getting
regular low-grade psychic beating it's
pretty good and and that's something
that you obviously wouldn't wish upon
anyone much less little kids yeah and by
the way the autism thing you know I
don't know whether your child is
high-functioning or not but it's
certainly the case that a lot of us have
the idea that we almost don't want to
deal with people who aren't in some
sense on the spectrum or having some
kind of ability to focus and and to work
with abstractions very often I think of
you know I I'm on top of this I'm color
blind and I always make the point that I
see camouflage you know that you're
wearing bright purple right now I'm stop
it
before I let my girlfriend now wife make
these decisions I make terrible you look
great yeah you looks great I'm sure I'm
something to do so that that that would
be one group here's another one that I
think is really important now I know
that you are the child of immigrants and
that you know I'm of course married to
an immigrant the temptation is for us to
sort of be very defensive of our
immigrants because we have some forces
at the moment that become very
jingoistic and I think that that's right
but I also think that we have to
recognize that there is a story about
immigration that's very unpleasant and
ugly which is how Americans have used
immigration to redistribute wealth
amongst ourselves and effectively the
immigrant is used as a tool of
redistribution then people get angry or
protective of the tool and one of the
things that I think that's very
important is assuming a huge chunk of
America is highly Xena Xena feel ik they
like foreigners they like traveling
abroad they're like you food music you
probably read righteous mind by Jonathan
Haidt you're probably friends with John
yeah yeah I figured continue because
this is what it reminds me of okay the
thing is is that Xena philic restriction
estar a good chunk of this country if
you do a poll and you allow for all four
boxes Xena Felix and
restriction astac span ssin Asst Zena
philic restriction ism is a giant cohort
nobody speaks to it because if you say
anything about restriction ism the media
will instantaneously label you as NF oh
can we at least distinguish the idea of
the immigrants as souls like ourselves
who have been an important part of our
national tapestry together with the fact
that very often they are used as
instruments of transfers of wealth I
agree and that we should be angry at our
fellow Americans who cynically use
immigration and hide behind the
immigrant to take money from one sector
and put it into their own pockets or you
should not be angry at someone who's
angry about the immigrants this is the
thing because because there's something
like you said it's like you know in some
ways someone can have a very legitimate
grievance right the fact that there have
been these instruments of a wealth
transfer that have been imported into
our midst so I call these the Americans
who redistribute our wealth immigrant
reproduce puppy dogs to redistribute our
wealth they'd use puppy dogs because
nobody can be against puppies right and
so it's a very cynical use of the Statue
of Liberty but something is very
difficult to talk about but it's
something that I've been talking about
for a while because I think that I'm I'm
so far in the Zen affiliate category
it would be comical if somebody decided
I actually had a problem so I've been
bold and I haven't really had the
problem but most Americans feel very
uncomfortable talking about immigration
because they have two different feelings
they one have a really good feeling
about the person that they know who
happened to come from Uganda or India
and they have the sense that something
is wrong with this story we're gonna
have to disentangle it and restore
something that makes us feel good about
it rather than uncomfortable I agree
great
yeah and you know I think I may be able
to help in this regard I think you're
perfectly positioned for this but you
know part I'm the son of immigrants who
loves this country loves that immigrants
have been incredible source of dynamism
but
I you know you can't have open borders
and unrestricted immigration I
understand the sentiment where people
are struggling with the fact that our
country has brought many people in
either intentionally or unintentionally
in ways that are changing our economy
and society in ways that in like some
people have in legitimate problems with
I think we need to be able to have an
open conversation about difficult topics
around this and pull them apart and the
fact is we need we need people to feel
comfortable that it's okay to feel
uncomfortable as long as you're trying
to explore them at the current president
from my money gets way too close to
jingoistic sentiments yeah and and
that's one of the natural reactions is
that if the current president says one
thing then you know the right thing to
do is say the exact opposite
but then the nuance gets lost and then
unfortunately we end up falling into
that's why you see authorized camps we
have it's so important not only to
defeat the current president but also to
defeat the kleptocratic center of of our
own party as well as the regressive left
that proposes as the progressive rep
left and then to take care of the
constituents that are currently all over
the spectrum in a new world and one of
the things I love about your slogan
which is not left or right but forward
right yes that's the slogan yeah and
that that thing is is that it is moot
it's a question it also happens to be
the truth it's not a static I know it's
moving out of flatland like we've been
we've been given this smorgasbord of bad
options and just say hey I don't think I
want to dine from there I think these
things are available off menu do you
mind if I if I you know like for example
Starbucks I think will sell you a short
cup of coffee but they won't put it on
the menu you have to know that to ask
for it so I like to think of you as the
guy who somehow knows that there are
things that aren't on the menu I am
animal-style it in and out
I'm Andrew yeah his animal style
let me get me man I I agree that I can
change the political conversation in a
way that many Americans find very
exciting and productive because 25% of
Americans are politically disengaged
including I'm sure some people watching
this and I believe it's up to 48%
self-identify as independent which is
almost twice what identify as other
demos - I dent affine is independent I
can't stand my own party but my feeling
is I have to stay there and say hey
we're out of control in order to save
the structure because I'd like you know
well the two-party system I mean I agree
that's what I'm why I'm running as a
Democrat in part it's like well you have
these two parties maybe you can turn one
of them into like a highly functioning
party with great ideas in the rest of it
I mean that's like an easier solution
than what I really want to do is I want
to reach I want the insurgency that you
and I have been sort of a part of this
loose collection of people who are
thinking completely off the menu to
start retaking our institutions we
always had heterodox people of high
caliber who are you know effectively
heretics housed inside the Harvard's and
MIT Zinn Caltex
and I think we've gotten rid of that
kind of where they are they're then
they're scared shitless to like say the
wrong thing or else though do you
remember the time the situation where
MIT turned over Aaron Schwartz and
laughs cos I mean it's dark we should
laugh no no I mean I'm for laughing at
the dark yeah I I laugh at the dark yeah
you know it's a it's like everybody
knows that but you're not allowed to do
it in public so screw that you know that
we had the situation with this guy Aaron
Schwartz you know Aaron no did you I've
it was a friend of friends yeah you know
and this guy almost certainly was a
pretty pure hearted human being who was
fighting a good fight and I suppose me
to shelter those people and instead they
cooperate you know in turning them over
as soon as you get the institutional
incentives in a particular direction and
like I mean this is not near and like
this is just like recent goods in recent
memory
but you know I stuck up for Shayne
Gillis this comedian that had said item
I saw that and the idea that you know
you were in a position to say look I'm
the candidate personally yeah and so if
anyone should be offended it's me and so
I think he shouldn't lose his job over
it well this is the thing that the
quality of mercy or forgiveness or just
recognition that there should be space
for remorse and redemption this is what
makes so much of the intolerant left
feel cult-like
and I thought what you were doing was
you were showing the best aspects of a
truly compassionate left I was trying to
be a human being you know like you look
at him being like well like the is that
a job losing a fence but then the fact
that NBC ended up firing him was
entirely consistent with our corporate
incentives because if you look at it say
like well is this person that we've
invested a lot in that some revenue
generator for us no because you hadn't
even worked for one day
it's like our corporate incentives to
can him and thus like you know put an
end to any controversy or advertisers or
whatnot that we be troubled by it yeah
so it's like so if you'd asked me it's
like hey do you think he's gonna be
fired I mean like yeah he's almost
certainly gonna be fired because that's
what the corporate incentives well I
understand that so one of the things
that I'm really interested in doing but
I still made me sad like I was like hey
this would be unusually human and
forgiving if they decided to well they
lost a teachable moment because one of
the things that's going on is that so
much of the information economy is very
very marginal in the sense that you're
almost producing a public good so for
example I slap ads on my podcasts and
when I start my sponsors now what I'm
trying well what I'm trying to do is
I've tried two new models one of which
I'm calling reverse sponsorship where I
shout out some great company which
doesn't know that I'm gonna say
something positive and maybe they become
sponsors maybe they don't but the other
one is risk vertices where people get to
know me over long periods of time and
the hope is that you're gonna say look
you're not gonna catch me being horrible
and bigoted in all of these things but I
might say something dangerous like
something
just said about immigration and will you
make sure that you will not run away
from me
during the period where the mob descends
and the frenzy is that it's worse now
right because if we don't fix the
economic models we can't have deeper
discussions because everybody's gonna
run away at the first sight of trouble
and so part of what we're trying to do
ultimately with the advertising is
pirate radio pre advertising what do you
think I mean I love it's like leave it
to you to try and solve that kind of
problem or I got some other things that
I want to talk about is demographics
oh yeah please okay so so so let me
first say I am a parent of a
neurologically atypical young person I
agree with you that I think that many of
people have a different perspective are
going to end up being contributors and
in highly distinctive ways I will say
that even kids who are not going to be
contributors in a highly distinctive way
still deserve schools that can support
and accommodate them and that to me
these kids are like the shorthand I use
is that their spiky you know it's like
you have very high capacities in some
respects or a different point of view
and then real challenges in other
respect and so if I send you into a
social environment where there are 30
kids for one teacher you're gonna have a
terrible terrible time you know and
that's 100% predictable and so if then
you have like a critical mass of people
that resemble this then you should try
and design an institution that takes
that into account and I feel so deeply
for families that struggle with this
like you struggle with it sounds like oh
absolutely experiencing it I am strong
with it and and you and Pia you know me
and Evelyn like we have an unusual level
of ability to try and you know manage
situation and I meet single moms around
the country who have you know autistic
or neurologically typical kids and that
don't have the means and they're they
live in a part of the country that does
not have like a lot of resources in
place for kids that are different and it
breaks my heart like it the fact that
there are all of these kids that are
heading into these schools that are
getting
you know more than low-grade psychic
beatings oh my god this is why I leave
my my DM is open on Twitter and this is
one of the number one things I do it for
is people write to me and they say I
know you're really busy but I just want
to tell you nobody had ever spoken to my
situation you're proud of something I'm
always ashamed of and I guarantee you
I'm not the first presidential candidate
with autism in the family yeah and the
fact that on the first talking about it
is to me long overdue and ridiculous and
a man and you know and I get I get some
of the same messages that you get but
you know like I want to actually try and
solve the problem for those families I
mean it makes me feel glad that they
feel spoken to and that they realize not
the only ones going through I want to
see I want to see more money going to
figure out how do we diversify the
classroom of the future yeah so that the
load isn't borne by people who don't fit
the economics of the teaching model yes
and part of it is that that we regard
the education of our kids is a cost and
so then the city then is like well I
can't afford to have like a teacher for
you're not a typical kid and so what we
have to do is talk about inverting the
model is you have to look at the
education of our children as an
investment and then you say what's that
like these kids require you know like
X&Y then we should make that investment
with the certainty and I share your
confidence in this that you have a
couple of those kids do something highly
atypical and remarkable then that pays
for whatever support or German I mean I
had a very well-known professor revealed
to me that he couldn't read papers in
his field I just can't read you know any
and he has to figure out what the paper
is likely to be saying there is such a
weird world of unexpected achievement
and this is the demon this is the demon
that we have to slay yes anyways is that
the negative externalities are not being
encompassed within the budgets of
various institutions very well so but
but then also where for
going all of the potential positive
value creation or generation from proper
investment in our human capital and
another dimension too and this is like
another here nor there but I was just
with Dean came in and in New Hampshire
and he was talking about how the FDA is
like all their incentives are just to
like regulate the shit out of anything
and then I said to him I was like you
know what they should start measuring is
the foregone utility of keeping
something away from from people like if
you had something and what is the
African like cost of the regulation yeah
he had like so he had like this
prosthetic limb that he was trying to
give to vets and the FDA was making it
really hard for him to do so he was like
are you kidding me I'm trying to give
limbs Tibet save it amputated and so by
you're making it hard for me to do so
like you multiply like all of the
limbless vets who aren't getting a limb
like you know it's like so if you had
that as like an actual measurement for
the FDA it's like you need to have these
companies internalize the negative
externalities of things like pollution
and the rest of it but you almost need
like our institutions like our schools
and our regulatory agencies to start
trying to somehow capture the potential
gains from investing in our kids or
allowing a certain innovation into the
market like that the the big problems
are that our measurements are really
primitive and it ends up and you end up
with binary incentives where you lose a
lot of the value and so you end up being
like hey don't have a teacher for your
kid so your kids gonna you know just end
up sidelined what well you know in
sidelined is like a euphemistic way for
saying destroyed I know one of the
things I wanted to do at some point I
actually ended up talking to the
Heritage Foundation of all people about
this was the idea of national interest
waivers so that we could have a
skunkworks with very light regulation
hanging off the side of every large
company and the idea that you would put
some portion of a company you could put
some portion of a company outside where
the rules were effectively different
because you needed people to take
massive risks yeah
to be able to move super fast to be
dealing with highly non neurotypical
people and this is one of the things
that drives me nuts about the political
conversation is like you get like they
get like yelled at for a particular it's
like oh you made a mistake but it's like
you kind of need to have an environment
where you're going to accept a certain
level of mistakes particularly when
you're talking about large-scale
society-wide investments where like of
course you can't get that stuff right
and you know it's like and that the
problem is that the political incentives
are for everyone to try and avoid like a
negative headline or something that
that's look a lot of us are very
disagreeable very difficult to deal with
and you know I saw you pick up
endorsements from people like Elon Musk
you know which is is then I hear his
personal life being criticized like I
don't really care
this guy is responsible for everything
this specie how much it V right how much
innovation if he's got a few four balls
let's give him some privacy let him be
in peace and just recognize that we're
getting an unbelievable deal and yet
this desire to somehow stamp out
outliers
I mean outliers are essential to the
American project yes I could not agree
more and and you know I I'd consider
myself it's pretty funny Eric cuz I you
know I think I had in many ways like a
highly conventional upbringing that help
like I feel like I'm sort of a hybrid
where to the extent that I was highly
contrarian or dissimilar that's like I
you know I came up through a series of
institutions in an era where you know I
think I learned to adapt but then I look
at my boys and I think to myself that
you know that that their way of life is
going to be very very different than
mine I'm sure yours too because we came
of age in a different era well this is
true I mean I was just talking about
this actually with Bret Easton Ellis
sitting in that chair that you know I
grew up as part of this free-range world
largely before Etan Patz got kidnapped
the milk carton kids changed everything
I worry about the sort of we were too
free-range and these kids are too
sheltered that we have to find some new
it makes but I want to get to another
give me one more demographic okay yes
let's do it
and then we'll close it out I want to
talk about something which really makes
me angry and excited I think that
America has without question some of the
finest sources educationally for
brilliance in STEM subjects and we've
pretended for a very long time that
Americans are not good at stem that we
are disinterested in stem that STEM
careers are fantastic when many of them
are pretty shitty and that we don't
recognize that the entire stem complex
is suffused with bullshit because the
model the economic model for investing
in basic research went belly-up
because the the universities were built
on a growth model that was unsustainable
yeah and I want to stop lying so one I
want to start recognizing that we have
high schools that have more Nobel Prizes
than all of China that we are using
Chinese labor and other Asian countries
not just because we are exporting
education is a good but because we have
a cryptic labor market in basic research
where we pretend people are students
when they're actually workers we pretend
that we're importing them to educate
them but actually what we're trying to
do is use a poverty differential we have
our own people who are really fantastic
because they're not very obedient and
instead people prefer obedient people
coming in who are aren't here on
temporary visas therefore they have to
follow orders the entire National
Science Foundation National Academy of
Science Complex is bizarrely suffused
with nonsense and because of this we
can't actually have the National
Academies adjudicate what's true because
they are the prime offender of this how
do we get back to a situation which we
can recognize that we have a Stuyvesant
or a Bronx science you know or Far
Rockaway or any of the
unbelievable high schools that are
turning out people who desperately want
to do STEM subjects they're not being
paid when they finally get their degrees
at appropriate levels yeah they've been
secretly studied by our science complex
because these career paths are known to
be crappy and we have completely
suffused this with a Mis description so
that nobody can actually fix any
problems
that's an incredible description and to
me the lack of proper resources for
basic research for things that ended up
being foundational for many of our
current industries
it's the biggest bargain in the world
it's just the future you're investing in
it's just right now we're so brainwashed
by market driven thinking that if
there's not some short-term
profitability tied to it or there's no
drug company funding in those lines that
and this is something that the
government historically has been the
leader in where that said you know what
we can lay the foundation and create
paths for people to be able to do basic
research the benefits of which will be
unclear they may not exist they may not
materialize for decades but it's similar
to what we're talking about with the
neurologically atypical kids is that
like a few of them pay off and then the
payoff can be unfathomably significant
what we call this long vol investing in
hedge fund land where most things don't
work out but a few that do pay for all
of the losers yep yeah and and right now
the the yeah that to me this is a role
where historically the government has
led and you need a government willing to
make long-term sustained investments
that may only pay off way down the road
and may not pay off but you still need
to be able to make them well so you know
the the other weird part of this is that
by using our own people and letting in
particular China know that it can't
operate a relatively totalitarian
government over there and have the
benefit of freedom over here with a
pipeline for all of our innovations to
immediately go back
over there China needs to be induced in
some sense to understand that they can't
get by without giving their people
freedom and what they're right now doing
is is that they're using our freedom and
a periscope by which they can see
everything that we're doing and if we
actually cut that off I know that the
universities are gonna scream bloody
murder but what's gonna happen is China
is gonna have to start investing in its
the right of its own people to give the
middle finger because irreverence is the
secret of American ingenuity yeah yeah
you know that this reminds me of a joke
that they told artificial intelligence
which is how far behind is China than
the US and AI and the answer is 12 hours
means they you know obviously they wake
up and then they see what we did I can't
tell you how fantastic it is they have
you come into the studio you're coming
off of this big rally in MacArthur Park
you're welcome anytime to come back I'd
love to continue the conversation is to
ban this this feels to me like half a
conversation we're gonna have to have
the second half at some other time so if
you enjoyed this convo let Eric know and
then hopefully I'll have me back and if
you'd like to join the yangyang you
should know we are a very very cheap
gang to join right well our average
donation is only $25 so our fans are
even cheaper than Bernie's which no one
even knew could be a thing in politics
but here it is but you get $25 times
enough people and you end up putting up
very very big numbers and you'll see
like we're already into the eight digits
as a campaign and we can take this whole
thing we can contend because a lot of
people watching this right now you're
you're ignoring politics as usual we can
actually have a different sort of
politics that takes real thinking real
ideas real solutions and brings them to
the highest levels of our government
it just needs enough Eric's and PS and
you are watching at home to say I prefer
this to the stuff I'm getting through
the cable TV network and one of the
things I think that's been great about
watching your meteoric rise is that you
are outside of control without being out
of control having
kind of a mature person who's not easily
bought or swayed his speaking in a way
that nobody knows what he's going to say
next has been hugely positive for the
entire process okay thank you
you know the only the only currency I
answer to is his ideas in humanity like
you you know you put a good idea in
front of me or a good person I listen
well you've been that way since before
all the success so we wouldn't we wish
you continued success and we'll have you
back here the next time you're in LA
with a little bit of time would love
that brother all right
thanks you've been through the portal
with Andrew yang presidential candidate
for 2020 and telling us to make America
think harder yes this man is gonna make
you think harder all the time all right
be well everybody
[Music]